Guide to the Historic Photographs and Drawings Collection Photo.002
New York University Archives
Historic Photographs and Drawings Collection
1800-1980
New York University Archives
Photo.002
261 objects
This collection contains photographs, drawings, glass plate negatives, and other documentary materials depicting student life and activities, campus architecture, city maps, faculty portraits, and other aspects of NYU culture from 1800-1980.
Historical Note
Included in this collection is a group of 161 glass plate negatives representing a period of NYU history from approximately 1890-1910. These glass plates were transferred to the University Archives, presumably from the historic collection at the former University Heights campus. This collection was maintained by Dr. Theodore Francis Jones, who published a centennial history of the University in 1933. The University Heights campus was opened by NYU in the Bronx in 1894 and was sold in 1973. It is now the campus of the Bronx Community College. Many of the glass plate negatives are images of the University Heights campus and some of its well-known architecture, including the Hall of Fame for Great Americans, which was built in 1900.
Some of the glass plate negatives include the signature "Sabin 08." This may be the signature of Raymond E. Sabin, a student at the University Heights campus who graduated in 1908 with a Bachelor of Science degree in Pure Science. Sabin was a member of the Camera Club at the Heights, Delta Phi fraternity, and the varsity football squad. He lived in Flushing, Queens.
Scope and Contents
The Historic Photographs and Drawings Collection is a compilation of multiple formats of materials depicting all aspects of NYU from campus architecture to student life and activities. The bulk of the collection is from the early to mid-20th century, with some materials dating back to the 19th century. The two series that make up this collection were originally individual collections that have been brought together by virtue of their physical formats and the focus of their content.
The oversized materials in the collection contain portraits of faculty members, maps of the University Heights campus as well as the Washington Square campus, group photographs of athletic teams, and photographs of events such as commencement and class reunions. Also included in the oversized materials are several reproductions of documents such as George Washington's Inaugural Address, the Mayflower Contract, the United States Constitution, and the First Patent of America.
The glass plate negatives in the collection focus primarily on the University Heights campus, its buildings, and student life and activities including sporting events and in class lectures. The glass plate negatives are extremely fragile, and despite their high quality and good condition, several of them are slightly cracked or damaged.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series, Series I: Oversized Photos and Drawings and Series II: Glass Plate Negatives.
Series I is arranged by topic. Series II has been kept in its original order.
List
Series I: Oversized Photos and Drawings
Series II: Glass Plate Negatives
College Presidents -- New York (State) -- Biography; Printed ephemera.; Floor plans.; Photographs.; Washington Square (New York, N.Y.); Architectural drawings (visual works); Drawings (visual works); College buildings.; Architecture -- New York (State) -- New York.; Student activities.; Glass -- Pictorial works.; College sports.; Commencement ceremonies; New York University. University Heights; New York University; New York University. Hall of Fame for Great Americans; New York University -- Presidents; New York University. Washington Square Campus; New York University -- Societies; New York University -- Students; New York University -- Buildings; New York University -- History
- Series I: Oversized Photographs and Drawings
  - Graduation, Class of 1885, 13.5x10 mounted black and white photograph Photo size: 13.5x8.5 Mounting size: 13.5x10 Recto: broken into two pieces, pieces missing, extreme discoloration/yellowing, dark stains on photograph, black printing on mounting Verso: writing in pencil, dark brown stains, extreme discoloration/yellowing Condition: Poor (Box Shared University Archives 127)
    Photographs.
  - Unidentified NYU class/club group, circa 1888; 15x12.5 mounted black and white photograph on fiber paper Photo size: 13.5x10 Mounting Size: 15x12.5 Recto: damage to the mounting- thick, glue-like substance, skinning and tearing, discoloration/yellowing of photo and mounting Verso: 2 types of writing in pencil, two sharp vertical lines of color distorion, flaking of mounting, stains, heavy surface dirt Condition: Fair (Box Shared University Archives 127)
  - Unidentified NYU class/club, circa 1920s; 14x11 black and white reproduction of a photograph General: rippling along edges Recto: slight cracks in upper right corner Verso: pencil writing Condition: good (Box Shared University Archives 122)
  - School of Commerce, Class of 1905, 14x11.5 black and white mounted photograph and mounted, printed label that has broken off. Recto: mounting is peeling, paper and adhesive on bottom of photograph where label appears to have been attached Verso: adhesive markings with attached bits of paper and secondary mounting, discoloration, skinning Condition: Fair (Flat-file 8, Drawer 3)
  - School of Commerce, Accounts and Finance Freshman Dinner, Class of 1917, May 15, 1915; 20x14 black and white photograph mounted Mounting Size: 20x14 Photo Size: 19x11 General: extreme discoloration/yellowing Recto: tear at bottom right corner, discoloration/yellowing,white writing from negative Verso: two types of pencil writing, skinning of mounting, stains and tears possible from adhesive removal Condition: Fair (Box Shared University Archives 122)
    Scope and content
    The location of this dinner is an unnamed Fifth Avenue restaurant.
  - Members of the first graduating class of the NYU School of Commerce, Class of 1902, 1918; 22x9 black and white photographic reproduction, process (possibly a photo of a photo)? General: planar distortion and curling Recto: tear on left side, curling, Verso: peeling adhesive that appears to be tape,tears and bends in corners Condition: Fair (Flat-file 8, Drawer 3)
  - NYU Summer School Chorus Sesquicentennial International Exposition, August 6, 1926; 19.5x7 black and white photograph on fiber paper General: break in center, extreme discoloration/yellowing, white writing from negative Recto: extreme discoloration/yellowing, white writing from negative Verso: Writing in black pen and pencil, attempt to repair the break using pressure adhesive that appears to be tape, small hole in right bottom corner, surface dirt. Condition: Fair (Box Shared University Archives 127)
  - NYU Band, 1936; 17x10.5 black and white photograph (includes 6.5x1.5 photo adhered on top of larger photo) General: yellowing/discoloration Recto: flaking, tear on right bottom corner that has been repaired with pressure adhesive, discoloration, stains, scratches Verso: heavy surface dirt, discoloration, numerous pressure adhesives to repair tears and breaks, writing in blue pen, writing in pencil General: Fair (Box Shared University Archives 127)
  - NYU Normal School, Class of 1904, circa 1904; 18x16 mounted black and white photograph Photo: 16x12 Mounting: 18x16 General:planar distortion Recto: mounting has broken off along left side, white stamp on mounting lower right corner, slight discoloration, slight surface dirt Verso: corner and edge tears in the mounting Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 127)
  - NYU Chinese Students Club Dinner, January 17, 1920; 18x10.5 black and white photograph Recto:severe tears and rips, pieces of other papers and photographs stuck on to the original photo, long break along the left side, white writing from negative, top right corner is missing Verso: heavy surface dirt, writing in pen dedicating photo to Chancellor Brown from King Y. Ling, pressure adhesives, tears, dark stains Condition: Poor (Box Shared University Archives 127)
    Photographs.; Waldorf Astoria Hotel (New York, N.Y.)
  - School of Law, Afternoon and Evening Divisions class portraits, 1922; 26x19.5 black and white mounted photograph photo and mounting board are equal in size General: corners are torn, hole in upper left corner, tears in the photo, edges of photo and mounting are worn down Recto: severe discoloration, torn corners, brown staining on edges, surface dirt Verso: brown discoloration, mounting is falling off of photograph- crumbling around the edges, brown spots Condition: Poor (Flat-file-folder 7)
  - NYU School of Law, Class of 1936, 19.5x15.5 black and white mounted photography reproduction(?) Mounting size and photo size the same size General: adhesive is starting to fail to hold photo and mounting together, planar distortion Recto: creases, tears, wrinkling, surface dirt, Verso: mounting is creased, stained and dirty possible from adhesives Condition: Fair (Box Shared University Archives 122)
  - The Bagatelle, NYU Varsity Show group photograph, April 23, 1914; 17x14 mounted black and white photograph on fiber paper Photo size: 13.5x10.5 Mounting Size: 17x14 General: discoloration/yellowing Recto: white writing from negative on bottom right corner, stamp on bottom right corner, ink pen on mounting above and below photo,skinning of mounting Verso: stains and tearing possible from adhesive, two types of writing in pencil Condition: Fair (Box Shared University Archives 128)
  - Class of 1878, 30-year class reunion, 1908; 10.5x8 black and white photo negative Verso: black writing with description of the photograph Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 122)
    Black-and-white negatives.
  - NYU Class of 1918 (Box Shared University Archives 145, Folder 6)
  - NYU Regiment, 301st Infantry group photograph, circa 1918; 20x10 black and white photograph on fiber paper (silver gelatin print?) General: extensive breaks, pieces missing from bottom of photo, curling- picture appears to have been rolled Recto: 8 breaks, multiple creases, piece missing from bottom left, surface dirt that appears to be a fingerprint Verso: writing in two different types of blue pen- names of some of the men pictured, heavy surface dirt,, breaks, ink smears Condition: poor (Box Shared University Archives 128)
    World War, 1914-1918; Photographs.
  - NYU, S.A.T.C. Group, 1918; 37.5x7.25 black and white photograph on fiber paper- broken into 3 pieces Piece #1- 10x7.25 Piece #2- 6.5x7.25 Piece#3: 21x7.25 General: multiple breaks and creases on each piece Piece#1 Recto: break on left side, multiple breaks along the bottom, surface dirt that appears to be black soot, writing in blue pen on bottom right corner, white writing from negative. Verso: writing in blue pen, pressure adhesive that appears to be tape- repairing tears and breaks, surface dirt and yellow discoloration Piece #2: Recto: break on right side, multiple breaks along the bottom, surface dirt that appears to be black soot Verso: pressure adhesive that appears to be tape- repairing tears and breaks, surface dirt and yellow discoloration Piece #3: Recto: four breaks, tear along right side, yellow stain on bottom left side, pressure adhesive applied along breaks, Verso: writing in two different types of plack pen, discoloration from pressure adhesive, multiple pieces of pressure adhesive to repair breaks, heavy surface dirt, Condition: Poor (Flat-file 8, Drawer 5)
    Conditions governing access
    Extremely fragile. May not be handled without archivist supervision.
  - Visit of Major General John F. O'Ryan, N.Y.N.G., to NYU, June 1919; 41x7.5 black and white mounted photograph General: broken into two pieces, severe discoloration, additional breaks and flaking Piece #1 19x7.5 Piece #2 22x7.5 Piece #1 Recto: uneven break on left side, label affixed to top, right corner with writing in black pen, severe discoloration (chemical burn?) on bottom, right side. Verso: sever discoloration, black lines, water stain(?) Piece #2 Recto: additional break along left side, uneven break along right end, discoloration, small pieces of the photograph have been torn off, Verso:heavy surface dirt, writing in blue colored pencil, water stain(?), mounting is flaking General: Poor (Flat-file 8, Drawer 5)
    Photographs.; O'Ryan, John F. (John Francis), 1874-1961
  - Unknown NYU Military regiment, circa 1914-1919; 26x10 black and white photograph General: broken into three pieces Recto: thesrs appears to be moisture in the frame, possible water damage, discoloration, heavy surface dirt, brownish stains on upper left corner Verso: not visible because of frame. Frame recto has heavy surface dirt, discoloration, blackened paper is flaking off of cardboard backing. Photograph was removed from frame on 04/13/09 after frame accidently broke. Condition: Poor (Flat-file-folder 6)
  - Unknown NYU class group photograph, circa 1904; 20x16 mounted black and white photograph General: secondary mounting with archivally sound board, sealed in mylar Photo Size: 13.5x10 Mounting Size: 20x16 Recto: writing in pen on original mounting, stamp on mounting, crumbling corners on mounting, cracks and tears in mounting, discoloration/yellowing Verso: verso not visible behind archival, secondary mounting Condition: Good (Box 28)
    Photographs.; Bragdon, Edmund
  - Unknown NYU class group photograph, undated; 20x16 mounted black and white photograph General: secondary mounting with archivally sound board, sealed in mylar Photo Size: 13.5x10 Mounting Size: 20x16 Recto: writing in pen on original mounting, crumbling corners on mounting, left top and right bottom corners broken off, cracks and tears in mounting, slight discoloration of photo Verso: verso not visible behind archival, secondary mounting Condition: Good (Box 28)
  - Unknown NYU class group photograph, circa 1904; 20x16 mounted black and white photograph General: secondary mounting with archivally sound board, sealed in mylar Photo Size: 13.5x10 Mounting Size: 20x16 Recto: stamped imprint on mounting, crumbling corners on mounting, bottom right corner is missing, cracks and tears in mounting, discoloration Verso: verso not visible behind archival, secondary mounting Condition: Fair (Box 28)
  - Brown, Elmer Ellsworth: Inauguration as Chancellor at NYU, November 10, 1911; 19x16 Black and White Mounted Photograph Photo size 13x11 Mount size: 19x16 General: brittle, planar distortion Recto: Discoloration- yellowing of mounting and photo, skinning of mounting, adhesive substance on mounting, slight scratches on photo, stains in right bottom corner of mounting, Verso: Heavy surface dirt that appears to be fingerprints, writing in black pen that describes the event and people pictured, writing in pencil, stamp by pictoral news co., stamps and manuscript on brown paper mounted to the secondary support and sized 11.25x14.5 Condition: Fair (Box Shared University Archives 128)
    Photographs.; Brown, Elmer Ellsworth, 1861-1934
  - NYU Commencement on Football field of University Heights Campus, June 9, 1948; 18.5x8 black and white photograph mounted on fiber paper General: in two pieces, mounted on fiber paper and taped Recto: discoloration and surface dirt along the hing, date and time inscribed on negative at the bottom left corner, Verso: surface dirt, writing from two pencil types, tape adhesive along the hinge Condition: Good (needs new mylar) (Box Shared University Archives 128)
  - NYU Commencement in Washington Square Park, 1979; 20x5 black and white enlarged Contact sheet print General: Recto: writing in what appears to be china marker and blue pen, bend in top right corner Verso: a number of brown stains, writing in pencil Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 128)
  - NYU Commencement in Washington Square Park, 1979; 20x7 enlarged black and white contact sheet print Recto:imprint from someone writing on top of the print, writing in what appears to be china marker Verso:dark stains that appear to be ink, writing in pencil, brown staining Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 128)
  - NYU Commencement (6 large-format contact sheets), circa 1980s; 20x16 RC print of enlarged contact sheet Recto:marks in red pen Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 128)
  - Faculty of the University of New York Medical Department: portraits, circa 1865-1967; 15x17.5 mounted photo montage (reproduction) stored in laminent(?) and should be rehoused) General: multiple breaks, pieces missing, extreme surface dirt and discoloration Recto: writing in pencil under each image, heavy surface dirt (soot?), breaks along left side, piece missing from right side, stains that appear to be from water or liquid, brown stains, Verso: heavy surface dirt, pressure adhesive attempting to repair breaks, writing in pencil, pieces of paper attached by adhesive Condition: Poor (Box Shared University Archives 128)
  - Faculty of Correspondence College at Cambridge: group photograph, circa 1893; 12x9.5 mounted black and white photograph Recto: yellowing/color distortion, pieces of photo and mounting are missing pieces Verso: label affixed by pressure adhesive, yellowing Condition: Fair (Box Shared University Archives 129)
  - Faculty of the College of Engineering, May 27, 1949; 24x8 black and white photograph on fiber paper General: breaks, curling, discoloration Recto: discoloration, numerous vertical creases- it appears that the photograph was rolled, white writing from negative Verso: numerous pressure adhesives, graph paper taped to the back of the photograph, brown and green lines and pencil writing, graph paper is folded in half, some stains from ahesives, pencil writing on photograph Condition: Poor (Flat-file-folder 4)
  - Mirabeau L. Towns portrait, 1912; 11x17.5 mounted black and white photograph on fiber paper Photo size: 10x13.5 Mounting size: 11x17.5 General: planar distortion, three pieces missing from sides Recto: calligraphy writing in black pen, writing in black pencil, white marks at bottom right, flaking off along the edges, beginning to break at top right Verso: yellowing/color distortion, flaking of mounting along the edges. Condition: Fair (Box Shared University Archives 128)
    Physical Characteristics
    Pieces of this item are missing.
    Photographs.; Towns, Mirabeau
  - Emily Warren Roebling: portrait in cap and gown, circa 1899; 11x14 black and white photograph on RC paper- reproduction (?) General: planar distortion/curling Recto: creases at corners, ripplig at edges, Verso: stamp in black ink from New York Historical Society, writing in pencil, markings in what appears to be blue marker, rippling at edges Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 130)
    This photograph was taken at a law school graduation, which may have been held at NYU.
    Photographs.; Roebling, Emily Warren, 1843-1903
  - NYU Chancellor L. Jay Oliva and Vice Dean of Education Elmer Baker, Jr., May 20, 1987; 14x11 black and white photograph with white border Recto: some rippling along edges Verso: writing in black pen, writing in pencil, some rippling along edges Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 129)
    Photographs.; Oliva, L. Jay (Lawrence Jay), 1933-2014; Baker, Elmer E., 1922-
  - Dr. L. Jay Oliva caricature as strongman, circa 1991-2002; 11x14 fascimile of photo and drawing collage Picture size: 8.5x11 Mounting size: 11x14 Recto: some service dirt on image, label affixed to mounting Verso: discoloration from pressure adhesive attaching image to mounting Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 129)
    Photographs.; Collages (visual works); New York University. University Heights; Oliva, L. Jay (Lawrence Jay), 1933-2014
  - John H. Prime, sixth Dean of NYU School of Commerce: portrait, circa 1962-1965; 11x13.5 black and white photograph on fiber paper Recto:white border, scratches and small rips on photograph Verso: discoloration from adhesive along the edges, writing in pencil Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 129)
  - John Brademas, circa 1981-1991; 11x14 black and white photograph on fiber paper Recto: tiny, white abrasions along edge Verso: writing in pencil Condition: Good Note: duplicate image in same file and negative stored with photograph (Box Shared University Archives 130)
    Photographs.; Brademas, John, 1927-2016
  - Isaac Ferris: photograph of portrait painting, circa 1853-1870; 16x20 color printed on RC paper Recto: color printing, some small wrinkles Verso: clean Condition:: Good (Box Shared University Archives 128)
    Physical characteristics
    This is a facsimile produced at an unknown date.
    Photocopies.; Ferris, Isaac, 1798-1873
  - G. Rowland Collins: portrait, circa 1931-1959; 11x14 mounted black and white photograph facsimile Recto: small, white scratches along the top, white border Verso: surface dirt, writing in pencil Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 130)
    Photocopies.; Collins, George Rowland, 1894-
  - Samuel Morse, circa 1855-1872; 11x14 black and white photograph with white border on RC paper Recto: slight bends on right side, rippling along edges Verso: writing in red ink pen, curling/rippling along edges Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 130)
    Photographs.; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872
  - Samuel F. B. Morse Portrait Sketch by Albert Rosenthal, circa 1883-1939; 17x24 black and white sketch in pencil/charcoal on fiber paper Recto: some surface dirt, smudges, 3 writings in pencil/charcoal Verso: heavy surface dirt, smudges, pressure adhesive holding together tear at bottom of paper Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 128)
  - Hugo Castello: portrait, circa 1977; 10x14 black and white photograph on fiber paper, Recto: bend in top left corner Verso: three types of writing in pencil, slight surface dirt Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 129)
    Photographs.; Castello, Hugo
  - Harvard Law School Faculty group photograph (from Derrick Bell Collection), 1977-1978 (Box Shared University Archives 129)
    Related materials
    This photograph is from MC 138, the Derrick A. Bell, Jr., Papers.
    Photographs.; Harvard University; Bell, Derrick A., 1930-2011
  - 1909 Dental School Faculty (Flat-file 6, Drawer 9)
  - Dental School Faculty, 1917 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 9)
  - Dental School Faculty Professors 1923 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 9)
  - Dental School poster describing a mural in the Student Lounge re: dental anesthesia, 1940 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 9)
  - Chorale Camp in Holiday Hills, NY: scrapbook, September 1979 (Box Shared University Archives 128)
  - Photograph of NYU Heights Campus- Library and Hall of Fame 1934, 14x11 black and white photograph on fiber paper General: planar distortion/curling Recto: bend on bottom left corner, small scratches, Verso: three writings in pencil, surface dirt and discoloration, especially along edges Condition: Good
  - NYU University Heights Campus- Student Activities- Montage Photograph, circa 1940s; 17x11.5 black and white photo montage Recto: Crease (near break) in center where it appears the image was folded, small tears along edges Verso: heavy surface dirt, crease in center, black spotting at bottom right corner Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 145, Folder 7)
  - Hall of Fame- Unveiling of Busts, ceremony under tent, May 13, 1924; 15.5x20 black and white mounted photograph Recto: photograph lifting off of mounting, mounting is crumbling along the edges Verso: mounting appears to be torn on top left and bottom right corners, pressure adhesive peeling off of mounting, scratches Condition: Good (Box Shared University Archives 127)